Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィの教えに基づいて インスピレーションを得たこのシリーズ
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
2つの相互に関連した領域間の進化的関係を 探求することを目的としています
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
人間の意識を全体のレベルと精妙なレベルで表現します
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
これは、現在の科学的理解と
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
人間の神経解剖学、特に自律神経系
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
そして、ヨガに関する伝統的な文献に記載されている いわゆる精妙なシステムです
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
最終的に、このシリーズは視聴者の皆さんを この探検の旅にご案内します
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィが教える 瞑想を通してこれらの関係を体験します
Today, we are diving into the fascinating intersection
今日は、神経科学とスピリチュアリティの
of neuroscience and spirituality,
興味深い関わりについて探求します
exploring how the human nervous system, the autonomic nervous system,
人間の神経系、自律神経系がどのように機能するかを探り
and the brain's unique organization relate to our spiritual experiences.
そして脳の独特な構造は 私たちの精神的な経験と関係しています
Join us as we unravel the mysteries of consciousness,
意識の謎を解き明かすために 私たちと一緒に参加してください
evolution's role in shaping the brain,
脳の形成における進化の役割
and the profound insights from ancient texts like the Bhagavad Gita.
そしてバガヴァッド・ギーターのような 古代の文献から得られる深い洞察
Did you ever wonder how our brains perceive spirituality?
私たちの脳が精神性をどのように認識するのか 疑問に思ったことはありませんか?
Or how ancient texts might align with modern neuroscience?
あるいは古代の文献が現代の神経科学と どのように一致するのでしょうか?
Get ready for a mind-expanding conversation that will challenge your understanding
あなたの理解力と視野を広げる会話をご覧ください
Let's start to uncover these and more intriguing questions with Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
アシシュ・プラダン博士と一緒に、これらの疑問や その他の興味深い疑問を明らかにしていきましょう
Dr. Pradhan is a distinguished medical leader who has led cutting-edge work
プラダン博士は、最先端の神経学および心臓血管医学の 研究を主導してきた
in neurology and cardiovascular medicine.
著名な医療リーダーです
And his career is a testament to strategic leadership
彼のキャリアは戦略的リーダーシップの証である
and a deep commitment to patient-centric care.
患者中心のケアに深く取り組んでいます
With a distinguished career spanning pivotal roles
重要な役割を担う輝かしい経歴を持つ
in drug development at multiple global pharma R&amp;D organizations,
複数のグローバル製薬研究開発組織での 医薬品開発に携わる
Dr. Pradhan has pioneered groundbreaking initiatives
プラダン博士は画期的な取り組みの先駆者であり
that redefine patient care and medical strategy.
患者ケアと医療戦略を再定義します
And throughout his career, Dr. Pradhan has led
そして、プラダン博士はキャリアを通じて
even greater innovative initiatives
科学の進歩と総合的な患者ケアを結びつける
that bridge scientific advancements with holistic patient care,
革新的な取り組みを行い
earning him accolades for his pragmatic approach and global impact.
彼は、その実践的なアプローチと 世界的な影響力で称賛されています
And in addition to this professional excellence, he is a longstanding meditation practitioner,
そして、この専門的な卓越性に加えて 彼は長年の瞑想実践者であり
coach, and mentor.
コーチ、メンターでもあります
Ashish was introduced to Sahaja Yoga as a meditation practice
プラダン博士は幼い頃にインドのムンバイで
at a very young age in Mumbai, India.
瞑想を実践するためにサハジャヨガを紹介されました
And having experienced its profound benefits, both personally and professionally,
そして、個人的にも職業的にもその大きな恩恵を経験し
Ashish has been a passionate advocate as well as an instructor
サハジャ瞑想法の熱心な支持者であり
of the Sahaja meditation technique.
指導者でもあります
Over the past decades, he has led seminars and workshops for introducing this meditation
彼は過去数十年にわたり、この瞑想を 紹介するセミナーやワークショップを
in multiple countries.
複数の国で主催してきました
And the experiences he has gleaned through these years of global interactivity
そして、これらの年月にわたる 国際的な交流を通じて得た経験は
have allowed him time to reflect on how best to introduce this meditation
文化的に多様な人々にこの瞑想を どのように紹介するのが最も効果的かを
to culturally-diverse audiences through the unifying language
彼が熟考するための時間を与えてくれました
of modern science.
その際の鍵となるのが 現代科学という共通の言語です
Welcome, Dr. Ashish, and it's such a pleasure to have you join us.
アシシュ博士、ようこそ ご参加いただき、大変嬉しく思います
Thank you, Monikaji. Thanks for having me.
モニカさん、お招きいただき ありがとうございます
Let's start by talking to our audiences a little bit about your meditation journey
まずは視聴者の皆さんに、この瞑想の創始者と
and the founder of this meditation.
瞑想の旅について少しお話ししましょう
Sahaja was established by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi
サハジャは、シュリ・マタジ・ニルマラ・デヴィによって 設立されました
as Sahaja Yoga in India.
インドではサハジャヨガとして知られています
It's also recognized as Sahaja Yoga Meditation or Sahaja Meditation around the world
これは1970年にインドでスタートして 世界中でサハジャヨガ瞑想
in 1970 in India.
またはサハジャ瞑想としても知られています
And it is a very simple, straightforward meditation technique
これは非常にシンプルで分かりやすい瞑想テクニックです
which, at its very core relies or is defined by the awakening
それは本質的には、私たち一人ひとりの仙骨に宿る
of a dormant energy that lies within each one of us
眠っていたエネルギーの目覚めから始まるもので
in the sacrum bone.
そう定義されています
And as we go into this series, we will talk a lot about
このシリーズでは、身体のさまざまな解剖学的な構造が
how the whole anatomical features relate to spirituality.
どのようにスピリチュアルな側面と関係しているかについて 多くを語っていきます
But the awakening of this energy and its ascent through the energy centers
このエネルギーの目覚めと、その後に続く 上方に位置するエネルギーセンターを通っての上昇
that lie above it, and its ultimate manifestation through the seventh energy center by piercing it,
そして最終的に第七のエネルギーセンターを 突き抜けて現れる現象
so-called in spiritual terms, is what meditation is truly about.
スピリチュアルな言葉で言えばこれこそが 本当の意味での瞑想なのです
But in fact, beyond that, it's what is called a yogic state.
しかし実際には、それを超えると ヨガの状態と呼ばれるものになります
So, this was something that Shri Mataji started in 1970.
これがシュリ・マタジが1970年に始めたものなのです
It is now practiced in over 110-120 countries around the world.
現在では世界110〜120か国以上で実践されています
At a very young age, my father took to this form of meditation practice,
父は幼い頃からこの瞑想法を実践していました
and that's how I took to it as well.
そして私も同じようにそれにハマったのです
And I was pretty young, about ten years old.
わたしは当時、10歳くらいで まだかなり幼かったんです
And thereafter, I have been a regular practitioner of this form of meditation.
それ以来、私はこの瞑想を定期的に実践してきました
So, Dr. Pradhan, before we embark on exploring the spiritual aspects of being human,
プラダン博士、人間の精神的な側面を探る前に
why is it crucial to first understand the complexities of our nervous system?
まず神経系の複雑さを理解することが なぜ重要なのでしょうか?
And how does this understanding lay a foundation for our spiritual journey?
この理解はどのようにして私たちの 精神的な理解の基礎を築くのでしょうか?
Excellent questions. So, the journey begins
素晴らしい質問ですね
with what it means to be human.
では、人間であることの意味を知る旅が始まります
So, when we say we are human beings, that is, we are Homo sapiens,
つまり、私たちが「人間である」と言うとき すなわちホモ・サピエンスであるということは
we are defined by a set of biological characteristics,
私たちがある特定の生物学的特徴
a set of genomic characteristics,
遺伝子情報の特徴
the way the genetic code defines us as humans.
そして遺伝子コードによって 人間として定義されているということなのです
So, for example, as everybody knows now in the twenty-first century,
例えば、21世紀の今、誰もが知っているように
we have 46 chromosomes within us.
私たちの体内には46本の染色体があります
So, those are both autosomes as well as sex chromosomes.
つまり、それらは常染色体であると同時に 性染色体でもあるのです
And that is what makes us human.
そしてそれが私たちを人間にするのです
The human genome project unraveled the entire genetic sequence.
ヒトゲノムプロジェクトにより 遺伝子配列全体が解明されたのです
Meaning, the chemistry of it could be written out.
つまり、その化学的な性質を 書き出すことができるということです
And if you read that, it can also be seen as just a set of alphabets
そして、これを読めば、それは単なる アルファベットの集まりとも言えるでしょう
of about six billion base pairs of how the genetic code is written.
遺伝コードが書かれている約60億塩基対のことです
But that could be done for every living organism that exists on the planet.
しかし、それは地球上に存在するあらゆる生物に対して 実行できる可能性があります
So, we have a particular genetic code that is unique to us.
つまり、私たちは特有の 遺伝子コードを持っているのです
Does that make us human?
それで私たちは人間になるのでしょうか？
So, what makes us human is not the common chemistry that binds us;
つまり、私たちを人間にしているのは 私たちを結びつける共通の化学反応ではありません
it's the same as in jellyfish, it's the same as in fish,
クラゲと同じで、魚も同じです
it's the same as in mammals, in vertebrates, in reptiles.
それは哺乳類、脊椎動物、爬虫類でも同様です
Every living organism has a genetic code. Does that make them human?
すべての生物には遺伝子コードがあります それで彼らは人間になるのでしょうか？
Well, what makes us human is a very unique capacity
では、私たちを人間たらしめているものとは何か
that, so far at least, we believe is very unique to us
それは、少なくとも現時点では 私たち人類だけに特有だと考えられている
as a species.
非常にユニークな能力なのです
And that is the ability to differentiate between what is self and non-self.
それは、自己と非自己を区別する能力です
And that defines us as a human being.
そしてそれが私たちを人間として定義するのです
It intersects science, philosophy, and religion.
それは科学、哲学、宗教が交差します
It is at this crucial intersection where we begin to define ourselves as humans.
この重要な交差点において、 私たちは自分自身を人間として定義し始めます
And therefore, at the very outset, as we begin this journey,
ですから、この旅を始めるにあたって
it is imperative that we realize, that we recognize, what it means to be human.
人間であることが何を意味するのかを私たちが理解し 認識することが不可欠です
And within that construct of what it means to be human
そして、「人間であるとはどういうことか」という構造の中には
is this, somewhere within us, almost a hard-wired system
私たちの中のどこかに、ほとんど生得的ともいえる システムが存在しており
that allows us to be able to differentiate between us as me, for example, I,
それによって私たちは、 「自分＝私」と「自分でないもの」とを
the sense of I-ness versus non-I-ness.
区別することができるのです
Every human being says, "This is my body, this is my person, this is me."
すべての人間は「これが私の体、私の人格、これが私」と言います
So, who is this "me"? What gives a human being the awareness
では、この「私」とは誰なのでしょうか？ 人間に意識を与えるものは何でしょうか？
to say, "This is I," versus somebody else?
「これは私です」と言うことと 他の誰かと言うことの違いは？
Do elephants do it? Do lions do it? Do tigers do it? Do salmon fish do it?
ゾウやライオンやトラはそうするのでしょうか？ サケはそうするのでしょうか？
Does a condor flying in the air do it?
空を飛ぶコンドルもそうするのでしょうか?
We, so far, do not know, but it is assumed, based on a number of experiments
今のところ正確には分かっていませんが、これまでに 行われてきた数々の実験に基づいて考えられているのは
that have been conducted, that the closest it comes to
この「自己」と「非自己」を区別する能力に最も近いのは
are the great apes, the orangutans, the chimpanzees,
オランウータンやチンパンジーといった
who can have this understanding between self and non-self.
大型類人猿である、ということです
And that, in essence, is the critical starting point to understand human spirituality and its origins.
そして、本質的には、それが人間の精神性と その起源を理解するための重要な出発点なのです
So, Dr. Pradhan, evolution has sculpted our brains over the millennia,
プラダン博士、進化は何千年にもわたって 私たちの脳を形作ってきました
something that you were already just touching upon.
先ほども触れた内容です
Could you paint a vivid picture of this evolutionary journey,
この進化の過程を詳しく教えていただけますか？
highlighting any fascinating adaptations that have shaped our brain structure and function
そして、私たちの脳の構造と機能を 今日のような驚異的なものへと形成してきた
into the marvel that it is today?
適応の数々を、ぜひご紹介ください
I am going to expand on that question,
この質問についてもう少し詳しく説明します
take a little bit of time to explain. It is a critical question.
少し時間をかけて説明してください これは非常に重要な質問です
So, let us start off at the very beginning.
それでは、最初から始めましょう
So, life as we know originated as single-cellular organisms in water.
つまり、私たちが知っている生命は 水中の単細胞生物として誕生したのです
As the planet was formed after the Big Bang,
惑星はビッグバンの後に形成されたので
it started cooling, the gases cooled down, the crust was formed, the oceans were formed,
冷え始め、ガスが冷えて地殻が形成され 海が形成されました
the elements came together,
要素が組み合わさり
and as the planet cooled down, at some point in time,
そして地球が冷えていくと、ある時点で
this unique chemistry came together of carbon-based elements
このユニークな化学反応は 炭素ベースの元素の組み合わせで起こった
and formed what we call life.
そして私たちが生命と呼ぶものを形成しました
So, it started off as unicellular organisms that, over billions of years, matured,
つまり、単細胞生物として始まり、数十億年かけて成熟し
grew first into plankton, then small fish, then bigger fish.
最初はプランクトンに成長し、その後小魚になり さらに大きな魚になりました
Gradually, they came up on land, became amphibians;
徐々に彼らは陸に上がり、両生類になり
then we had one of them: reptiles.
そのうちの1つが爬虫類です
Mammals are a subgroup of vertebrates characterised by a spine
そして爬虫類からは脊椎動物と 無脊椎動物が生まれました
that is, one with the vertebral column: mammals,
つまり脊柱と一体化した哺乳類
and then, of course, us, as part of the mammalian species.
もちろん、哺乳類種の一部としての私たちも 生まれました
If we take a look at some of the most primitive life forms,
最も原始的な生命体のいくつかを見てみると
what they exactly are is a single cell or a multicellular organism
それらは正確には単細胞生物か多細胞生物か
that indulges in the most basic of functions.
最も基本的な機能に重点を置いたものです
It eats, it consumes nutrients, it somehow survives, it reproduces,
食べ、栄養を摂取し、何とか生き延び、繁殖し
and comes to an end at some point in time,
そしていつか終わりを迎える
and the cycle repeats itself.
そしてこのサイクルは繰り返されます
So, if you look at the structure of these organisms,
これらの生物の構造を見ると
what we see are rudiments
私たちが目にするのは神経系と呼んでいる
of what we call the nervous system.
原始的なものです
The nervous system is a system
神経系は、電気生理学的な電流を
that allows electrophysiological currents to be generated.
発生させることができるシステムです
If you think of what a nervous system is, think of it as electric currents
神経系とは何かを考えるとき それを電流として考えてみましょう
that are generated. These are voltage changes that happen
細胞膜を越えて生成される
across cell membranes.
電圧の変化です
So, like, if you take a voltmeter and put it across,
例えば、電圧計を横につなげてみると
you can see the changes that happen across a membrane,
膜を横切って起こる変化を見ることができます
and it is called a transmembrane potential.
それは膜電位と呼ばれます
So, why is this important? It seems to go a little deeper
では、なぜこれが重要なのでしょうか？
into the question you are asking, but this is important,
あなたが尋ねている質問に対して これはとても重要です
because life, literally, is electricity.
なぜなら、生命とは文字通り電気であるからです
Life, literally, is defined by the presence of an electric charge.
生命は文字通り、電荷の存在によって定義されます
So, for example, (and I will get back to the question you are answering),
例えば、（ここであなたが答えている質問に戻りますが）
but this is again important.
しかし、これもまた重要です
For example, when life comes to an end, even particularly in human beings,
例えば、生命が終わるとき、特に人間の場合
we say it is not just when the heart stops, but it is when the brain stops.
心臓が止まるだけでなく 脳が止まることもあると言われています
It is called brain death.
それは脳死と呼ばれます
So, when that electrical activity that exists,
つまり、存在する電気活動は
not just within the heart that causes the heart to pump,
心臓を動かす心臓の中だけでなく
but also the brain waves, they come to an end.
脳波も同様に、終わりを迎えます
And the reason these brain waves are actually formed
そしてこれらの脳波が実際に形成される理由は
is because of the movement of sodium and potassium
膜を越えて起こる、ナトリウムとカリウムの動きによるものです
So, back to what we're discussing. If you look at the most primitive forms of life,
さて、話に戻りましょう 最も原始的な生命体を見てみると
they do not have a well-developed nervous system.
それらは十分に発達した神経系を持っておらず
They just seem to have these minor, sort of, threads of electrical impulses
次々と現れる小さなネットワークのようなもので
that are just like a small network that keeps on popping up.
多少の電気的な刺激を持っています
And that is how we say the cell is alive.
これが細胞が生きていると言える理由です
Fast forward, what we see, if you take a look at the phylogenetic nature,
系統学的性質を見てみると
if you go from fish to reptile to basic mammal to, say, man.
魚類から爬虫類、基本的な哺乳類 そして例えば人間へと進化していくとします
For example, you take a fish, you take a serpent,
例えば、魚や蛇を取ったり
you take a mouse, and then a human brain, what we find is that the basic requirements
マウスと人間の脳を例に挙げると 基本的な要件は
for maintaining vegetative functions - breathing, locomotion - that is, movement,
呼吸、運動、つまり動きといった 植物機能を維持するために
food or nutrition or that acquisition, digestion, excretion, and reproduction,
食物や栄養、あるいはその獲得、消化、排泄、生殖
basic functions of life - these are present,
生命の基本的な機能 - これらは存在し
or started growing as evolution progressed.
あるいは進化が進むにつれて成長し始めました
We do not know why that happened — whether it was Darwinism, evolutionary pressures,
なぜそれが起こったのかは分かりません ダーウィン説なのか、進化の圧力なのか
natural selection, descent through modification, everything that Darwin wrote
自然選択、修正による系統樹などの ダーウィンが書いたものすべて
and has since been discussed and debated — all of that somehow came together.
それ以来、議論や討論が続けられてきましたが そのすべてがどういうわけかまとまりました
But the nervous system started evolving.
しかし、神経系は進化し始めました
It started becoming more and more sophisticated in terms of being able to respond
対応能力の面でますます洗練されてきました
to changes in the environment.
環境の変化に応じて
If you are a small fish, all you are worried about is not being gobbled up
あなたが小さな魚なら、より大きな魚に ただ食べられてしまうことだけを心配します
by a bigger fish. If you are a bigger fish,
もしあなたがより大きな魚なら
all you are worried about is not being gobbled up by an even bigger fish.
あなたが心配しているのは さらに大きな魚に飲み込まれないことだけです
Therefore, imagine being a fish in an aquatic environment:
したがって、水中環境にいる魚を 想像してみてください
you need sensory organs, you need to detect movement.
感覚器官が必要で、動きを感知する必要があり
We must be able to perceive sound and other waves
音波ではなく、何かを聞く必要があります
so gradually we need eyes
音波だと水中で簡単に繁殖することはできないので 徐々に目が必要になります
or what we call visual organs to be able to see if a larger organism
あるいは、より大きな生物が
is moving towards you.
あなたに向かって動いているとすると
It is hypothesized that, somehow, these evolutionary pressures,
何らかの形で、これらの進化圧力が
these survival needs, started creating and putting pressure in a way
これらの生存ニーズは、ある意味で圧力を生み出し始め
that what we call today 'the nervous system' started evolving.
私たちが今日「神経系」と呼んでいるものが 進化し始めたのです
Fast forward a few billion years, and what we now find in the human brain
数十億年早送りすると、今人間の脳の中にあるものが
is a highly evolved system which has two basic strata.
2つの基本層を持つ高度に進化したシステムです
The first strata is in the paleocortex—the old brain —
最初の層は「古皮質（パレオコルテックス）」 つまり古い脳にあたります
which takes care of the vegetative functions,
この部分は、生命維持に関わる機能や
the fear or the fight response,
恐怖や闘争反応といった
the basic kind of response; and above that
基本的な反応をつかさどっています。
is what we are going to be talking about the most, probably,
そしてその上に位置しているのが
which is the cerebral cortex.
おそらく私たちが最も多く語ることになるであろう 「大脳皮質」です
It is the cerebral cortex which is the most magnificent
神経学的な観点から見て 進化が生み出した最も驚異的な創造物こそが
creation of evolution
この「大脳皮質」なのです
from a neurological perspective, and that is critical to know,
これは非常に重要なポイントであり
and, hopefully, that allows us, as we move forward in our discussion today,
今日の議論を進めていく上での出発点として
as the basis of where we go.
私たちがこれをしっかり理解していることが望まれます
I would like to ask, doctor, that in the Bhagavad Gita
先生、バガヴァッド・ギーターの中で
there is a striking metaphor of a tree growing upside down with the roots in the brain.
脳に根を張り、逆さまに成長する樹という 印象的な比喩があります
Now, could you delve into the depths of this metaphor
神経科学の視点からこの比喩の深層に踏み込み
through the lens of neuroscience,
それが私たちの「心」の理解に対して
illuminating its profound implications for our understanding of the mind?
どれほど深い意味を持つのかを 明らかにしていただけますか？
The Lord Shri Krishna, in the Bhagavad Gita, in the fifteenth chapter,
主シュリ・クリシュナはバガヴァッド・ギーターの第15章で
describes a tree which is upside down,
逆さまの樹を表現しています
and the stanza that describes it says there exists a tree with its roots in the brain,
そしてそれを説明する節では 脳に根を張った樹が存在すると述べられています
and its branches that grow downward, and its leaves are like the Vedas,
その枝は下向きに伸び、その葉はヴェーダのようであり
and the one who knows or has knowledge of this tree
そしてこの樹について知っている人 あるいは知識のある人は
is a master of the Vedas.
ヴェーダの達人だと
Now, the Vedas, as you know, are considered probably the most ancient scriptures
さて、ご存知の通り、ヴェーダはおそらく 最も古い聖典と考えられています
that delve into philosophy but, most importantly, spirituality.
哲学を掘り下げますが、最も重要なのは スピリチュアリティです
So, what does this mean? How does this apply?
では、これはどういう意味でしょうか？ どのように適用されるのでしょうか？
Probably a more succinct explanation of the nervous system does not exist
おそらく神経系について、バガヴァッド・ギーターで 述べられているような
in as few words as has been described in the Bhagavad Gita.
これ以上簡潔な説明は存在しないでしょう
How does this correlate?
これはどう相関するのでしょうか?
The brain, which exists up here, is called the central nervous system,
この上部に存在する脳は、「中枢神経系」と呼ばれ
the brain and the spinal cord.
脳と脊髄から構成されています
It is made up of literally billions and billions
それは文字通り何十億もの
of its functional unit,
基本的な機能単位である
its basic functional unit called the neurons.
「ニューロン（神経細胞）」から構成されています
The neurons have a cell body,
ニューロンには細胞体があり
and they have a long tail which is called an axon,
そこから「軸索（アクソン）」と呼ばれる 長い突起が伸びています
and these axons, they come down and they pass through,
この軸索は下へと伸びて脊髄を構成する一部となり
constituting our spinal cord as well;
さらに脊柱（背骨）を通って外に出ていきます
then they come out
外に出ていきます
of the vertebral column as well as from parts of the brain,
また、脳の一部からは「脳神経」として
called the cranial nerves or the spinal nerves,
脊髄からは「脊髄神経」として出ていき
and they innervate the entire human body.
これらが人間の全身に神経を張り巡らせているのです
So, literally, if you think about it in metaphorical terms, you have a tree;
つまり、比喩的に考えるなら、私たちの体は まるで一本の「樹」のようなものです
the animation will make this very clear.
このことはアニメーションを見れば 非常によく分かるでしょう
The tree which has its roots in the brain, the branches as they get out,
その「樹」は、脳に根を持ち、そこから枝が伸び
and they circulate and they are spread across the body,
全身に広がり、循環していきます
and they innervate even the smallest sort
そしてその枝は、私たちの指先のような 最も小さな部分にまで神経を張り巡らせ
of the final tips of our fingers and every part of our body,
身体のあらゆる部分を支配しています
and that is what is referred to by Shri Krishna in the Bhagavad Gita as the leaves;
このイメージこそが、バガヴァッド・ギーターの中で シュリ・クリシュナが語った「葉」に相当するものなのです
and why it is important for us to understand,
そしてなぜこの理解が重要かというと
when it is said that the knowledge of this is the knowledge of the Vedas,
「これを知ることはヴェーダの知識を得ることである」 と言われる理由は
is that because this anatomical infrastructure provides the substrate through which we can gain
この解剖学的な構造が私たちの「心」や「条件づけ（思い込み）」 を超えた現実の理解
a realization or an understanding of reality that goes beyond the interpretation
すなわち「真の認識」や「悟り」へと至るための 基盤（サブストレート）を提供してくれているからです
of either our mind or of our conditionings, and that is true knowledge; it is true 'Vida.'
これこそが「真の知識」、つまり「ヴィダ（Vidya／知識）」なのです
'Vida' means knowledge, as the founder of Sahaja has always said,
「ヴィダ」とはサハジャの創始者が常に言っていたように 知識を意味します。
and the knowledge of this tree is only gained through self-awareness.
そしてこの知識の「樹」は 自己認識を通してのみ得られるのです
That energy that is present within us, when that energy is awakened,
私たちの中に存在するエネルギーが目覚めると
we realize the true nature of this tree, its branches, that is, the nerves,
私たちはこの「樹」の本当の姿 つまり神経という「枝」、そしていわゆる「葉」の意味を
and the so-called leaves.
真に理解することができるのです
So, as the founder of Sahaja, Shri Mataji, has expressed,
そこで、サハジャの創始者である シュリ・マタジは次のように述べています
and She said to me also, a number of times, in the privileged conversation that we had,
そして彼女は、私たちが交わした特別な会話の中で 何度も私にこう言いました
that Sahaj, essentially, is a function of our nervous system.
サハジは本質的には 私たちの神経系の機能であるということです
Human spirituality is not predicated, is not dependent on our cardiovascular system,
人間の精神性は、心臓血管系に依存するものではなく
our digestive system, our endocrine system. No.
消化器系や内分泌系でもありません
Human spirituality and its experience is a function of our nervous system,
人間の精神性とその経験は神経系の機能であり
and that is exactly where Shri Krishna was going when He explained that in that very short stanza
そして、まさにクリシュナがバガヴァッド・ギーターの
in the Bhagavad Gita.
あの短い詩節の中で説明した通りです
This is so interesting, and I am sure so many of us
これは本当に興味深いお話ですね
have not had a chance to get to that kind
そして、私たちの多くがこのような解釈に触れる機会を
of interpretation, and thanks so much for explaining that to us.
これまで持てなかったのではないかと思います 丁寧に説明してくださって、本当にありがとうございます
Could you shed light on the intriguing connections between our physical nervous system
私たちの「物理的な神経系」と 「霊的なサトルシステム（微細なエネルギーのシステム）」という
and the abstract notion of a spiritual subtle system,
抽象的な概念との間にある興味深いつながりについて ご説明いただけますか？
and how might our neural processes
また、私たちの神経の働きが、 より深いスピリチュアルな体験と
relate to a deeper spiritual experience?
どのように関係しているのかについても ぜひ教えてください
So, let's start off with the gross anatomy and the physiology of the nervous system,
それでは、解剖学と神経系の生理学から始めましょう
a quick primer, and then we will move towards the subtler aspect of it
簡単な入門書を書いてから より微妙な側面について見ていきましょう
and how they correlate.
そしてそれらがどのように相関するか
So, as we discussed in the previous question, the human nervous system comprises
前の質問で議論したように、人間の神経系は
the central nervous system, that's the brain, the spinal cord and then you have
中枢神経系、つまり脳と脊髄
the peripheral nervous system as well, which are these nerves,
そして末梢神経系も、つまりこれらの神経は
and a part of that is the autonomic nervous system.
その一部が自律神経系です
So, a lot of what we will discuss moving forward, and in the subsequent episodes,
今後のエピソードで議論する内容の多くは
will relate to this critical function, which is the autonomic nervous system.
自律神経系という重要な機能に関係します
So, let's take a moment to sort of understand what is what.
それでは、少し時間を取って 何が何であるかを理解してみましょう
The brain and the spinal cord, which is the central nervous system,
脳と脊髄は中枢神経系であり
relates to both, as we discussed earlier,
先ほどもお話ししたように、両方に関係しています
vegetative functions as well as our volitional functions:
栄養機能と意志機能
thinking, creativity, planning, etc.
思考力、創造力、計画力など
All are functions of this beautiful thing we call the cerebral cortex.
これらすべては、大脳皮質と呼ばれる この美しいものの機能です
Besides that, we have locomotion, that is, movement, and I am sitting here right now,
それに加えて、私たちには移動、つまり動きがあり 私は今ここに座っています
I know where my joints are, I know where my legs are,
関節がどこにあるか、足がどこにあるか
my eyes are looking and perceiving reality as we see around us.
私の目は私たちの周りで見る現実を見て 認識しています
A critical part of understanding this, and I am going to take a couple of minutes
これを理解する上で重要な部分なので
to explain this because this is important.
数分ほどお時間をいただき説明します
Reality, as a human being perceives it— and this is absolutely fascinating—
人間が認識している「現実」とは— これは本当に興味深いことですが
reality, as every human perceives it,
実はすべて、脳による解釈にすぎないのです
is an interpretation of the brain.
つまり、私たち一人ひとりが捉えている現実は 脳が作り出した「解釈された現実」なのです
It takes a while for this to sink in, because the brain itself is completely covered
これを理解して実感するには少し時間がかかります
within the cranium. It does not interact with the outside world.
なぜなら、脳というのは頭蓋骨の中に完全に覆われていて 外の世界と直接やり取りすることはないからです
The eyes receive impulses through the environment.
目は環境を通して刺激を受け取ります
The ears get sound waves, and they create impulses— again, electrical impulses.
耳は音波を受け取って、それを電気的インパルスに変換します つまり、いずれも「電気信号」として脳に伝えられるのです
Both from the eyes and the ears, as well as from the environment around,
目や耳からだけでなく、周囲の環境からも
sensory receptors that exist within the skin and the rest of the body
皮膚や体の他の部分に存在する感覚受容器
are all brought up into the brain, and it is the brain that interprets those signals.
すべて脳に送られ、それらの信号を解釈するのは脳です
For example, I am looking at a camera as this is being recorded.
たとえば、これを録画するとき、私はカメラを見ています
My eyes are seeing it, I am hearing myself, I am speaking in the English language.
私の目はそれを見ており、自分の声を聞き 英語で話しています。
There are literally millions of processes that are going on in this place right now.
まさに今この場所で 何百万ものプロセスが進行しています
Because I was born in an era and grew up in an era
なぜなら、私はこの「カメラ」と呼ばれる 機械を知っている時代に生まれ
where I know that this machine that I am looking at,
その時代に育ってきたからです
and looking at you,
今こうしてあなたを映しているこの装置が 「カメラ」と呼ばれるものだと
is called a camera. I know the word for it.
私は知っているし、その言葉も知っています
I know what it does. I know it is a recording device.
それが何をするのか知っています 録音機器であることも知っています
It will record an image. It will record my voice.
画像を記録し、私の声も録音します
But imagine if I came from an era, just a few hundred years ago,
でも、もし私がカメラが何なのか知らなかった
when I did not know what a camera was.
数百年前の時代から来たとしたら
My eyes would still be able to see it, but not recognize it.
私の目はそれをまだ見ることはできるが それが何だか認識することはできません
So, with the same exact object, based on my prior understanding of it,
つまり、同じ物体でも これまでの過去の理解に基づいて認識するので
my reality changes.
私の現実は変わるということです
So, it is still a camera.
カメラは依然としてカメラのままです
It will still do exactly what it is designed to do.
設計されたとおりの動作をそのまま実行します
But because I don't have an understanding of it, my reality of it changes, of how I see it.
しかし、私はそれを理解していないので それに対する私の現実、私の見方は変わります
I am speaking in English; if somebody doesn't understand English, they will say,
私は英語で話していますが もし英語が分からない人は
"What is he talking about?"
「彼は何を話しているんだ？」と言うでしょう
If somebody speaks in a language that I don't understand
もし誰かが、私が言っているのとまったく同じことを 私の知らない言語で話したとしても
and says the exact same things I am saying,
私はそれを理解できません
I don't understand it because I don't have knowledge
なぜなら、その人が話している言語についての知識が
of the language that that person is speaking in.
私にはないからです
And this is very important. This is very, very important to understand
スピリチュアルな話に入る前に
before we get into spirituality.
これを理解することが非常に重要です
Because reality, again, is what we perceive it to be.
なぜなら、現実とは、私たちが 「認識」しているものだからです
And there is a ton of literature about spirituality that says that the world we see around us
そして、私たちの周囲にある世界は実は 「幻（イリュージョン）」にすぎない
is really an illusion.
ということを語っているスピリチュアリティに関する文献は 非常にたくさん存在します
Now, of course, the literalist, and from the scientific point of view,
さて、もちろん文字通りに解釈する人 そして科学的な観点から言えば
that is nonsense. Black is black, white is white,
それはナンセンスです。 黒は黒、白は白、
red is red, blue is blue, green is green. Why?
赤は赤、青は青、緑は緑だと なぜでしょう？
Because the eye can perceive the wavelengths of visible light based on the spectrum.
なぜなら、私たちの目は可視光のスペクトルに基づいた波長しか 感知することができないからです
So, whether you know green is green or not, you may not know the word,
緑が緑であるかどうかは知らないかもしれませんが その単語は知らないかもしれません
but ten people, unless they have visual impairment, are going to see green as green and red as red.
しかし、視覚障害がない限り、10 人の人々は 緑は緑、赤は赤として見るでしょう
So, within that framework, reality is the same.
つまり、その枠組みの中では現実は同じです
But where it changes, where it starts becoming somewhat different, is when we talk about things
しかし、それが変化して、少し違ってき始めるのは 私たちが物事について話すときです
just as I gave an example of the camera.
カメラの例を挙げたのと同じです
All of this is important. Why?
これらはすべて重要です。なぜでしょうか?
Because that just tells us,
つまり、私が少し時間をかけて説明したということです
I took some time to explain it. So, my apologies if this was a bit long-winded.
少し回りくどくなってしまったかもしれませんが どうかご容赦ください
But it is important to realize because reality, as a human being perceives it,
しかし、これはとても重要なことなのです
depends on his or her prior conditionings
なぜなら、人間が認識する「現実」というものは、 その人のこれまでの条件づけ（思い込みや経験）
and their understanding and their background knowledge.
理解力、そして背景知識に 大きく依存しているからです
If I were to be shown a picture that hangs in the Louvre
もし私がルーヴル美術館に飾られている
of a lady with a very mysterious smile,
とても神秘的な微笑みを浮かべた 女性の絵を見せられたとしたら
considered to be the most famous painting in the world,
それが「世界で最も有名な絵画」だということから
perhaps I would recognize it as the Mona Lisa.
おそらく私はそれを「モナ・リザ」だと認識するでしょう
But imagine somebody who has never heard of Mona Lisa,
しかし、もし「モナ・リザ」という名前も
who has never heard of Da Vinci,
「ダ・ヴィンチ」という人物も聞いたことがない人が その絵を見たとしたら
sees that painting and may not recognize it, because he or she might appreciate the beauty.
その人はそれが有名な作品だとは気づかないかもしれません とはいえ、美しさ自体には感動するかもしれません
This is not to take away from the aesthetic sense of the individual,
これは個人の美的感覚を奪うものではありません
but he may not recognize it as the Mona Lisa, the perhaps most famous painting in the world.
しかし、彼はそれをおそらく世界で最も有名な絵画な モナ・リサだとは認識しないでしょう
All of this is important. Why? Because the world we inhabit,
これらはすべて重要です。なぜでしょうか？ なぜなら、私たちが生まれてから死ぬまで生きているこの世界は
from the time we are born to the time we die, depends on how our brain has been programmed.
大きく左右されるからです
Now, let's move to the essence of your question.
さて、質問の本質に移りましょう
Spirituality is not dependent on, or seeks to elevate an individual above, their conditionings,
スピリチュアリティとは、個人の条件づけに依存するものではなく むしろそれを超えていこうとするものです
above their state of knowledge, above whatever their educational status
それは、その人の知識のレベルや、 教育によって学んだこと・学ばなかったことといった
may have taught them or not.
あらゆる状態を超越しようとするものなのです
Whatever their socio-economic conditionings may have brought upon them.
たとえどのような社会的・経済的な条件づけがあろうとも
Whatever their cultural upbringing may have induced upon them.
また、どのような文化的な背景や育ち方をしていようとも それに左右されることはありません
We are all products of our culture, our societies, our beliefs, our educational status,
私たちは皆、自分の文化、社会、信念、 教育レベル、そして経済的な立場といったものの産物です
our economic status. Spiritual reality is completely above it all.
しかし、スピリチュアルな現実は、 それらすべてを超越したところに存在しているのです
So, to come back to that example,
さて、その例に戻ると、
why is spirituality different,
では、なぜスピリチュアリティはそれらと異なるのでしょうか？
or how is it correlated?
あるいは、それとどのように関係しているのでしょうか？
There exists within us a subtle system that is very different and is universal.
私たちの内側には、非常に異質でありながら普遍的な 「精妙なエネルギーのシステム（サトルシステム）」が存在しています
Just as the human brain and the spinal cord
人間の脳や脊髄、神経、末梢神経系が普遍的なものであるように
and the nerves and the peripheral nervous system is universal,
「スピリチュアルなシステム」とも呼ばれる
the subtle system, so-called, which is the spiritual system,
このサトルシステム（微細なエネルギーのシステム）もまた 普遍的なものです
is very different,
ただし、それはまったく異なる性質を持っており
and it has some anatomical correlates with the gross nervous system.
一方で、肉体的な神経系との間に いくつかの解剖学的な対応関係も存在しています
So, like we have the autonomic nervous system, which has a sympathetic component
私たちの身体には自律神経系があり
and a parasympathetic component, likewise, we have within us a subtle system
そこには交感神経系と副交感神経系という 二つの要素がありますが
that has the so-called energy channels, energy centers, and a way in which a human being,
それと同じように、私たちの内側には「サトルシステム」と呼ばれる 微細なエネルギーのシステムが存在しています
any human being on the planet, can experience reality
このサトルシステムには、「エネルギーチャネル」や 「エネルギーセンター」があり
completely agnostic of their cultural, philosophical,
これを通じて、地球上のどんな人間でも
spiritual, educational, linguistic background.
その人の文化的・哲学的・精神的・教育的・言語的な背景に関係なく 現実を体験することができるのです
It is definitely interesting to understand how spirituality expands an individual
スピリチュアリティが、どのように個人を さまざまなかたちで広げていくのかを
in different ways that you have explained, and I am sure, along the course of this series,
理解するのは、本当に興味深いことです
we will get to hear more from you
そして、このシリーズを通じて 先ほどあなたがお話しされていた
about that subtle system that you were talking about.
「サトルシステム（微細なシステム）」について もっと詳しくお聞きできることと思います
If you could paint us a picture of the human nervous system,
人間の神経系について
revealing its intricate functions and the fascinating structure,
その精巧な働きや驚くべき構造を 描き出していただけますか？
and as we zoom out, how does the autonomic nervous system
そして、視点を少し広げていったときに、 自律神経系はこの壮大な神経のネットワークの中で
fit into this grand neural tapestry,
どのように組み込まれていて
orchestrating our bodies' responses beyond conscious control?
私たちの意識を超えたところで 体の反応を巧みに調整しているのでしょうか？
So, the autonomic nervous system, so-called autonomic,
自律神経系、いわゆる自律神経は
has its own volitional system.
独自の意志決定システムを持っています
How does this happen?
これはどうして起こるのでしょうか?
If I start exercising, my heart rate will go up.
運動を始めると心拍数が上がります
Why? Because my muscles will need more oxygen; oxygen is carried by blood;
なぜでしょうか？それは、筋肉がより多くの酸素を 必要とするからです。酸素は血液によって運ばれます
blood needs to be pumped out at a much faster pace and much greater force.
血液はより速いペースとより大きな力で 送り出されなければなりません
So, the adrenaline will start being pumped out,
アドレナリンが分泌され始めます
and it will constrict my blood vessels, and it will also increase the contractile force
血管を収縮させ、収縮力も増加させます
of my heart, which will increase the pressure within the system,
心臓の圧力が高まり
and voila, I get more oxygen because I get more blood.
すると、血液量が増えるので酸素も増えます
Likewise breathing, likewise digestion; we don't control these processes.
呼吸も消化も同様です 私たちはこれらのプロセスを制御できません
When I eat something, I don't have to tell my stomach
何かを食べるとき、それを消化しろと
to go ahead and digest it.
胃に言う必要はありません
I don't have to tell my intestines to go on moving the food forward.
私は自分の腸に、「食べ物を先へ送れ」 と指示する必要はありません
All of these are beyond our conscious control. We don't have to think about it.
これらはすべて私たちの意識的な制御を超えています 考える必要はありません
That is the autonomic nervous system.
それが自律神経です
The autonomic nervous system arises from two parts in the human body.
自律神経系は、人間の身体の二つの部分から成り立っています
The first is in the brain, and the other one,
ひとつは脳にあり
is in the sacrum, which is at the bottom
もうひとつは仙骨 つまり背骨の一番下の部分にあります
of the vertebral column, as you can see in the animation.
このことは、アニメーションでもご覧いただける通りです
It is called the craniosacral outflow.
これは「脳仙髄系（craniosacral outflow）」 と呼ばれています
The sympathetic nervous system, which complements
自律神経系を補完する
the autonomic nervous system,
交感神経系も
also originates in the brain.
脳にその起源を持っています
Remember the original thing that Shri Krishna spoke about,
シュリ・クリシュナが語った最初のことを思い出してください
or that's in the Bhagavad Gita.
あるいはバガヴァッド・ギーターに書かれていることを
That also starts from the brain, and it also emerges from the spinal cord.
これも脳から始まり、脊髄からも出ています。
So, the autonomic nervous system has two components:
つまり、自律神経系には2つの要素があります
the parasympathetic and the sympathetic.
副交感神経と交感神経
These two systems function complementary to each other.
この二つのシステムは、 互いに補い合うかたちで機能しています
They do not antagonize each other,
これらは互いに対立するものではなく
but they complement each other.
補完し合う関係にあります
For example, the sympathetic nervous system will increase the heart rate.
たとえば、交感神経系は心拍数を増加させます
It will help in those kinds of actions.
そういった行動に役立ちます
The parasympathetic, on the other hand, will slow down the heart rate,
一方、副交感神経は心拍数をゆるやかにし
and it will increase, for example, the flow of the peristalsis, or promote peristalsis,
たとえば蠕動運動――つまり消化管内で 食べ物を移動させる動きを促進する働きがあります
which is the movement of food in the gastrointestinal tract.
それは消化管における食物の移動です
So, the parasympathetic and the sympathetic
つまり、副交感神経と交感神経は
nervous systems function as complements to each other.
神経系は互いに補い合うかたちで機能しています
How does it all work? In the brain, as we said, we have these
一体どうやって機能するのでしょうか？ 先ほど述べたように、脳の中には
very small nerve bodies called neurons.
ニューロンと呼ばれる非常に小さな神経細胞が存在しています
The nerves start from there, through the axons.
神経はそこから軸索（アクソン）を通じて伸びていきます
They come out of the brain in the form of cranial nerves,
それらは脳からは脳神経というかたちで出てきて
and then they also come out from the spinal cord.
さらに脊髄からも神経が伸びています
These nerves branch out,
これらの神経は文字通り枝分かれして
literally branch out,
体のさまざまな器官
and they enter the various organs, the entire organ system.
あらゆる臓器系に入り込んでいきます
So, our eyes, our ears, our lungs, our heart,
つまり、目、耳、肺、心臓
stomach, duodenum, pancreas, you name it,
胃、十二指腸、膵臓、生殖器、腎臓
the reproductive organs, kidneys. All of them are innervated.
どの器官であっても すべて神経が張り巡らされているのです
Think of a tree with its branches going out,
枝が伸びている木を思い浮かべてください
and these tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny thread-like structures.
そこには、非常に細くて糸のような構造が 無数に伸びています
The expression in medicine is innervation.
医学用語では、これを「神経支配（innervation）」 と呼びます
They penetrate into these organs.
それらはこれらの臓器に浸透します
And that is how the autonomic nervous system controls these functions:
そして、このようにして自律神経系は これらの機能をコントロールしているのです
the heart rate, respiration, gastrointestinal system,
心拍数、呼吸、消化器系、内分泌系などは
our endocrine system, by these nerves that are penetrated.
こうした神経が張り巡らされることによって 制御されています
So, that is your hardware. If you think in terms of hardware and software,
これがハードウェアです。ハードウェアと ソフトウェアの観点から考えると
that is the anatomical hardware.
これが解剖学的なハードウェアです
These nerves that penetrate these organs,
これらの神経は臓器に入り込み
and based on whether they are parasympathetic nerves
それが副交感神経であるか交感神経であるかによって
or whether they are sympathetic nerves, have different neurotransmitters,
使用される神経伝達物質が異なります
chemicals that drive the function
これらの神経伝達物質、すなわち化学物質が
of those organs.
各臓器の機能を動かしているのです
So, that in essence is your autonomic nervous system.
つまり、それが本質的に自律神経系なのです
The word is important because, again, it is outside of volitional control,
この言葉（＝「自律神経」）が重要なのは、 それが「意志によるコントロールの外」にあるからです
and that is a good thing because otherwise, it would be impossible to survive
そして、これは実はとても良いことなのです なぜなら、もし私たちがそれを意識的に制御しなければならなかったら
on a minute-to-minute basis.
一分一秒ごとに生き延びることすら 不可能になるからです
Now, a couple of quick points.
さて、いくつかポイントを簡単に述べます
What is the main function of the autonomic nervous system?
自律神経系の主な機能は何ですか？
The autonomic nervous system's primary function is to maintain milieu intérieur.
自律神経系の主な役割は、 「内的環境（milieu intérieur）」を維持することです
It is a kind of a French expression. What does that mean?
それは一種のフランス語表現です どういう意味ですか？
It ensures that the internal environment in which the organism exists
それは、生物が存在する内部環境が
is maintained in a state of balance.
常にバランスの取れた状態に保たれるようにすることです
That word is critical; that function is vital.
「ミリュー・アンテリウール（内部環境）」という言葉は 非常に重要であり、その機能は生命維持にとって不可欠です
So, if I exercise, to go back to the original example,
たとえば、先ほどの例に戻ると
my heart rate can go up,
運動をすれば心拍数は上昇します
but at some point, it does need to be brought down.
しかし、ある時点でそれを下げる必要があります
Because if it just keeps on going and going and going,
なぜなら、それがずっと続くと
at one point, my heart will fail.
ある時点で、私の心臓は機能不全に陥るでしょう
So, that's why if there is acceleration, there has to be deceleration.
ですから、加速があれば減速も必要になるのです
If there is forward movement, that forward movement, at some moment, has to stop,
前進するならば その前進はいつか止まらなければならない
and it has to slow down.
そして速度を落とさなければなりません
Let's think in terms of, for example, when we eat food and we have peristaltic movement,
たとえば、私たちが食べ物を食べたときに起こる 「蠕動運動（ぜんどううんどう）」を考えてみましょう
so the food goes down, stomach, duodenum, jejunum, ileum, etc.,
食べ物は食道を通って胃、十二指腸、空腸、回腸へと進み その後、大腸へと送られていきます
and then it goes into the large intestine. All of this is maintained in this absolutely,
これらすべての過程は、 非常に複雑でありながら 完全に統合されたシステムによって
impossibly complex but completely integrated system.
絶えず調整・維持されているのです
The two components of the autonomic nervous system constantly talk to each other.
自律神経系の2つの構成要素は 常に相互に通信しています
They don't function in their own cycles, and that's also very important
それぞれの器官が独立して バラバラに機能しているわけではなく
from a spiritual point of view.
すべてが一つの連動したサイクルの中で 働いているということも非常に重要なポイントです
So, maintaining that internal balance and addressing the requirements of the organism,
つまり、体内のバランスを維持しながら、 生体が必要とすることに対応していくこと
as things move along, as the environment around that individual changes, is very important.
それは時間の経過とともに、あるいはその個体を取り巻く 環境が変化する中で、非常に重要なことなのです
In common parlance, if you do Google searches or you look at YouTube videos,
一般的に言えば、Google検索をしたり YouTube動画を見たりする場合
the autonomic nervous system, they say,
自律神経系について「闘争か逃走か（fight or flight） に関係しているもの」
it's something that helps you with flight or fight.
という説明がよく見られます
If I go, if I am walking, if I am walking in a jungle,
もし私がジャングルを歩いているときに虎を見かけたら
I see a tiger, my brain recognizes this is danger, I need to start running,
私の脳は「これは危険だ」と認識し 「逃げなければ」と判断します
my heart rate will go up because, immediately, I need to start running, the body knows it,
その瞬間、心拍数が上がります すぐに走り出せるように、体がそれを理解して準備するのです
off I go. That's flight.
そして私は走り出します これが「逃走」という反応です
But if there is a smaller danger that I can maybe fight it,
もし危険が小さくて、それと戦えるなら
same thing, flight or fight responses.
同様に、逃走反応または戦闘反応が起こります
But throughout our evolution, through measures that we really do not understand,
しかし、私たちの進化の過程で 私たちが本当に理解していない仕組みや
through mechanisms that are yet to be elucidated, this system developed within organisms,
いまだに解明されていないメカニズムを通じて このシステムは生物の中で発達してきました
and it is present in mammals, but it is most developed in human beings.
このシステムは哺乳類にも存在していますが 最も高度に発達しているのは人間の中です
And it is very, very, very important to know it because the subtle system that we shall discuss
そして、それを知ることは非常に重要です なぜなら、次のエピソードでお話しする「精妙なシステム」は
in the next episodes is the microcosm; the subtle system is the microcosm
まさに「ミクロコスモス（小宇宙）」であり その精妙なシステムは、マクロコスモス（大宇宙）を反映しているものです
that reflects the macrocosm that, at a gross level, is the autonomic nervous system.
そしてそのマクロコスモスの「粗雑なレベルでの現れ」が 自律神経系なのです
Thank you so much for this very detailed explanation,
非常に詳細な説明をありがとうございました
and this also covers the next question
そして、ちょうどこのことが 伺おうとしていた次の質問にもつながります
that I had for you, which was how do the parasympathetic
それは 副交感神経系と交感神経系という
and sympathetic branches distinguish from each other,
二つの枝がどのように異なっていて
and how they interact with each other
また、それらが互いにどのように作用し合いながら
to maintain the body's balance and essential functions, etc.
身体のバランスや重要な機能を保っているのか といったことです
This brings me to the last question for today, and the question is about the nerves.
さて、今日の最後の質問になりますが 質問は緊張についてです
So, nerves are like the body's electrical wiring, or at least so we heard.
つまり、神経は体の電気配線のようなものだと お聞きしました
But how exactly do they transmit messages,
しかし、これらは具体的にどのように メッセージを伝達するのでしょうか？
and why are they crucial for our senses and movements?
そして、それらはなぜ私たちの感覚や 動きにとって重要なのでしょうか?
So, if you could take us into that electrifying world
では、ぜひその「電気的な世界」、すなわち神経の世界へと 私たちを連れていってください
of nerves, and also at the same time,
そして同時に、私たちの神経系、自律神経系 それらの神経が
talk to us about how our nervous system, the autonomic nervous system, and the nerves
人間の「スピリチュアルな精妙なシステム」 という概念とどのように
intertwine with the concept of the human spiritual subtle system?
絡み合っているのかについても お話しいただけたらと思います
So, nerves are
つまり、神経は
like the electrical wiring.
電気配線のようなものです
They are cells, and the way they function is through impulse generation and conduction.
それら（神経）は「細胞」であり、その働き方は「インパルス（電気的刺激）」を 発生させ、伝導することによって機能しています
Impulse means an electrical impulse.
インパルスとは電気的な刺激を意味します
If you think of this, my hand, as a membrane of the cell membrane.
これを私の手、細胞膜の膜として考えてみましょう
You have sodium and potassium. These are two positively charged ions
ナトリウムとカリウム、 これらはどちらも正の電荷を持つイオンです
that go across the cell membrane, and when they go across the cell membrane —
これらが細胞膜を通って移動するとき
so, potassium going out, sodium coming in —
つまり、カリウムが外へ出て、ナトリウムが内側に入ると
they create a change in the electrical charge
細胞膜の表面における
across the surface. So, nerve impulse or propagation is
電気的な電位（電荷）の変化が生じます つまり、「神経インパルス」あるいは「伝導」とは
the traveling of this impulse along a line.
この電気的なインパルスが 一方向のラインに沿って移動していく現象のことです
Let's say this is the beginning of the nerve, this is the end; the impulse is generated here,
仮に、ここが神経の始まりで、ここが終わりだとしましょう インパルス（神経信号）はここで発生し
and down it goes.
そこから下へと伝わっていきます
So, that's exactly how the electrical charge travels.
つつまり、これが電気的な信号が伝わる仕組みです
Of course, in an electrical wire, it's different.
もちろん、電気の配線とは仕組みが異なります
It's actually an electrical charge,
電線では、実際の電荷が流れますが
which is very different, from a movement of potassium and sodium ions
神経ではカリウムイオンとナトリウムイオンが 細胞膜を通って動くことによって
across membranes.
電気的な変化が生じるのです
This somehow creates awareness. We don't know exactly how it creates it,
これが何らかの形で意識を生み出します それがどのように生み出されるのかは分かりませんが
but we are aware, as we are aware. It's a state that is
私たちはそれに気づいています
different from when we are asleep. So, this state of awareness is important.
それは眠っているときとは異なる意識です ですから、この意識状態が重要なのです
We don't know exactly how it is created
それがど脳の中でどのように生成されるかは 正確には分かっていませんが
within the brain, but that electrical impulse generation
この電気的インパルスの生成こそが
is what, literally, as we said before when we answered one of the first questions,
まさに、先ほど最初の質問に答えたときにも言いましたが
is what life is about.
「命」とは何か、ということなのです
The way it functions is that when the electrical impulse arrives at a point,
その仕組みは、電気インパルスがある点に到達すると
it causes the release of certain chemicals; they are neurotransmitters.
特定の化学物質、つまり神経伝達物質が放出されます
So, they could be acetylcholine, they could be dopamine,
それはアセチルコリンだったり、ドーパミンだったり
they could be serotonin in the brain and in the rest of the organs.
脳や他の臓器ではセロトニンだったりします
It could also be adrenaline. These are neurotransmitters that then
また、アドレナリンである場合もあります これらはシナプスを通って伝達されます
are transferred across synapses.
シナプスは、神経系、特に脳において 非常に重要な部分です
Synapses are a very, very important part of the nervous system, particularly in the brain.
では、シナプスとは何か？ それを見てみましょう。これが質問への答えにもなります
So, what is a synapse? Let's take a look at it. That also helps to answer your question.
神経は一端で終わり、 そこから別の神経が始まります
The nerve comes up at one end, ends there, and then the other one begins,
そしてその間には小さな隙間があります それがシナプス間隙と呼ばれるものです
and there is a little bit of a gap. It's called the synaptic cleft.
神経インパルスが来て 神経伝達物質を放出し
The nerve impulse comes, releases the neurotransmitter,
それがもう一方の神経を活性化させて インパルスが伝播していくのです
it activates the other part, and the impulse is propagated.
シナプスは非常に重要です。なぜか？ それは私たちが後で見ることになりますが
Synapses are important. Why? Because when we will see,
私たちが脳をもっと深く見ると
when we will take a deeper look at the brain itself,
ニューロン同士が互いに接続し
neurons form connections with each other.
この接続が脳の働きに不可欠であることが分かります
And these connections are critical for the functioning of the brain.
そしてこれは仮説ですが 誰も完全には理解していません
And it is hypothesized, because nobody has nearly understood it,
なぜなら、私たちの脳には数十億個のニューロンがあり
because we have billions of neurons, billions.
それぞれが他のニューロンと絡み合い 接続されているからです
Each one of them interlaced and connected with other neurons.
それは集団であり ネットワークなのです
It's a collective; it's a network.
数十億×10は数兆にもなります そして、こう言われています
Because billions times ten becomes trillions, it is said that what makes us human,
私たち人間を人間たらしめているのは 最終的にはこのシナプスの接続性なのだと
at the end of the day, is our synaptic connectivity.
それは私たちの皮質の豊かさによって もたらされるのです
It is the richness of our cortex that makes it so.
だからこそ、神経は非常に重要なのです なぜなら
And that is why these nerves are so important, because,
もしこれを微積分の関数で考えるならば 積分関数のようなものです
like an integral.
積分のように
It's an integral function of all of these trillions of synapses, all firing together,
この数兆ものシナプスがすべて一斉に発火する 私たちの中に存在するネットワークが
this network that exists within us, that constitutes consciousness.
意識を構成しているのです
That's the hypothesis. And it is what essentially distinguishes us
それが仮説です そして、それが本質的に私たちを
from other species on the planet.
この地球上の他の種と区別しているものなのです
So, the nerves function as individual components of a vastly complex,
神経は、極めて複雑で絡み合った 統合されたネットワークの
interlaced, integrated network that ultimately not only creates life,
個々の構成要素として機能しており 最終的には生命を生み出すだけでなく
but makes us human.
私たちを人間にしているのです
This is really interesting, and this is very useful information, Dr. Ashish.
本当に興味深いですね そしてこれは非常に有益な情報です、アシシュ博士
I can't thank you enough for this very insightful discussion today.
今日の非常に洞察に満ちたお話に 心から感謝いたします
We hope to connect with you in our next episode
次回のエピソードでもまた
on yet another topic for a deeper understanding
視聴者のためにより深い理解を目指して
of our audiences.
別のトピックでお話しできることを願っております
And we would now like to take our audience to experience the state of meditation
それではこれから この瞑想の創始者によるビデオを通して
with a video from the founder of this meditation.
瞑想の状態を体験していただきます
And it will be easy for you to follow along.
簡単にできる内容になっています
We wish you all the very best on this meditative journey.
この瞑想の旅が素晴らしいものとなりますように
Thank you so much. Thank you, Dr. Ashish.
本当にありがとうございました アシシュ博士、感謝いたします
Thank you, Monikaji.
ありがとう、モニカジ
Shri Mataji: Not much is written, except that we can say it is written, "I will appear before you
シュリ・マタジ： 多くは書かれていませんが 「私は炎の舌のようにあなたの前に現れる」と記されています
like tongues of flames." These are the centers, the chakras.
これらは、すなわちセンターでチャクラです
And it is also said that there is a tree of life.
そして「生命の樹」があるとも言われています
Like Shri Krishna has described in Gita that the tree of life is upside down.
シュリ・クリシュナがギータの中で生命の樹は 逆さまであると述べているように
The roots are in the brain, and the branches go down in all directions.
根は脳にあり、枝はあらゆる方向に伸びています
Keep your eyes closed.
目を閉じてください
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
まずは右手を胸に当ててください
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
常に左手は私の方に向けてください
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
ここで、心の中で誠実に「母よ、私はスピリットですか？」と
Ask the question three times in your heart.
3回質問してください
This is a very fundamental question.
これは非常に基本的な質問です
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
次に、右手をお腹の左側
in the upper part.
上部に当ててください
Here press it.
ここを押してください
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
これが、いわゆるあなたのマスタリー（熟達）、ガイダンス（指導） グル・タットヴァのセンターです
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
それで、質問してください、母さん、私は自分自身の指導者ですか?
This is the question to be asked three times.
この質問を3回行ってください
Mother, am I my own master?
お母さん、私は自分自身の指導者ですか？
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
次に、右手をお腹の下部、左側に移動させてください
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
ここはすべての神聖な仕事が行われるセンターです
all the pure work is done.
すべての純粋な仕事がここで行われます
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
このセンターには6枚の花弁があるため
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
「母よ、私に純粋な知識を与えてください」
Six times you just ask.
と6回お願いしてください
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
この祈りにより、クンダリーニが目覚め始めます
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
クンダリーニの上昇を助けるには 協力しなければなりません
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
右手をお腹の左側、上部に移動させてください
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
お腹の上部を押してください
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
ここで、自信を持って「母よ、私は自分自身のマスターです」 と10回言ってください
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
これは10の戒律であり、「母よ、私は自分自身のマスターです」 と言ってください
This you have to say ten times.
これを10回言います
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
これらはあなたが言わなければならない十戒です
that Mother, I am my own master.
母よ、私は自分自身の指導者です
Now, ten times with full confidence.
さあ、自信を持って10回
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
では、右手を胸に当ててください
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度、自信を持ってこう言いましょう
Mother, I am the Spirit.
「母よ、私はスピリットです」
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
これは真実です。あなたはスピリット（聖霊）なのです
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
完全な自信を持ってこう言いましょう 「母よ、私はスピリットです」
This you have to say twelve times.
これを12回言いましょう
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
全能の神は「愛の海」であるということを 知らなければなりません
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
神は赦しの大海なのです
So He forgives.
だから神は許します
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
あなたがどんな悪いことをしても、神は許してくれます
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
だから罪悪感を感じずに右手を
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
左側の首と肩の付け根に当てましょう
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
ここでもう一度自信を持って言いましょう
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
「母よ、私には罪悪感はありません」
Sixteen times.
16回言いましょう
I am not guilty at all.
私には罪悪感はありません
Please say it.
言ってみてください
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
次に、額に手を当ててください ここは非常に重要なセンターです
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
ここでは心から言ってください、 「母よ、私はすべての人を許します」
Please say it from your heart.
心から言ってください
How many times is not the point.
何回でも結構です
Mother, I forgive everyone.
「母よ、私はすべての人を許します」
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
許すのは非常に難しいと言う人もいるでしょう
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
しかし、私たちが許さない、あるいは許すというのは幻想なのです
We do not do anything in both the cases.
どちらにしても、実際には私たちは何もしていません
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
けれども、もし許さなければ、 私たちは誤った力の手中に落ちてしまいます
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
だから、どうか心から言ってください。 「母よ、私はすべての人を許します。」
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
今度は、手を後頭部のアギャチャクラ（同じセンター）に 当ててください
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
頭を手の上に預け、少し後ろに押し下げてください
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
ここでは、あなた自身の満足のために言ってください
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
なぜなら、あなたはいつも罪悪感を抱えているからです 「おお、神よ、もし私が何か間違いを犯していたなら
please forgive me.
どうか私をお許しください」
Please forgive me, from your heart.
どうか心から「私をお許しください」と言ってください
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
次に、手を大きく広げて、手のひらの中心を
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
頭頂部の泉門（フォントネル）に当ててください それは子どもの頃に柔らかかった場所です
Press it hard.
強く押してください
Press hard your scalp.
頭皮をしっかり押します
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
そして、ここで7回、円を描くように強く動かしながら、 次のようにお願いしてください
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
「母よ、どうか私にセルフリアリゼーションをお与えください」 私はそれをあなたに強制することはできません
So you have to ask for it.
ですから、あなたがそれを求めなければなりません
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
7回、強く押しながら、頭頂でしっかり回してください
Slowly saying that.
ゆっくりと、「母よ、どうか私にセルフリアリゼーションをお与えください」 と言いながら